Guide to the Peter Starr Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Peter Starr papers
1758-1829
MS 955
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
(21 boxes)
Sermons of Peter Starr, together with the sermons of his predecessor in Kent (now Warren), Connecticut, Sylvanus Osborn, and of two relatives by marriage, John Keep and John Stevens. Three-fourths of the papers are by Peter Starr. During the Revolutionary War Starr shifted his loyalty, and the sermons provide biblical justification on both sides. John Keep was a chaplain during the war and a number of his camp sermons are in the collection.
Starr, Peter, 1744-1829
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from the Yale Divinity School Library in 1952 and 1979.
The Peter Starr Papers were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from the Yale Divinity School Library in 1952. Additional sermons of Peter Starr were transferred to the papers from the Sermons, Addresses and Discourses Collection of the Archives and Manuscripts division of the Divinity Library in 1979.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Peter Starr Sermons. II. Sylvanus Osborn Sermons. III. John Keep Sermons. IV. John Stevens Sermons. V. Miscellaneous Sermons.
Scope and Contents
Series I, PETER STARR SERMONS, contains sermons written by Peter Starr between 1769 and 1829. The sermons are arranged chronologically except where no date was discernable. The undated items are arranged by biblical texts, either Old or New Testament. Undated funeral sermons and fragments of sermons are grouped together. There are a few items that are not sermons: a journal dated 1771, notes taken for preparing sermons, and minutes of church meetings. The sermons prior to and during the Revolution reveal Starr's shift of loyalty, with biblical justifications for each side of the conflict at different times.
Series II, SYLVANUS OSBORN SERMONS, is arranged chronologically, from 1758 to 1770, with undated sermons at the end.
Series III, JOHN KEEP SERMONS, contains sermons written between 1770 and 1783. They are arranged chronologically with undated items at the end.
Series IV, JOHN STEVENS SERMONS, contains sermons written between 1780 and 1793. They are arranged chronologically according to numerical notation on the documents, with undated items at the end.
Series V, MISCELLANEOUS SERMONS, contains undated and unidentified sermons. These sermons may have been written by individuals included in the other series or by other ministers whom Peter Starr knew. Positive identification has not been possible.
Note: For additional papers concerning the family of Peter Starr, see the Starr Family Papers in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection. These are primarily papers of the children of Peter Starr and members of other families related by marriage.
The Robbins Family Papers also contain sermons and other papers of the family of Peter Starr's first wife. The Joseph Bellamy Papers, MS. Group No. 609, contain correspondence, sermons, and other papers of Peter Starr's teacher, Joseph Bellamy.
Biographical / Historical
PETER STARR (1744-1829)
Peter Starr was born in September, 1744, the youngest child of Samuel and Abigail (Dibble) Starr, of Danbury, Connecticut, and grandson of Captain Josiah and Rebekah Starr, also of Danbury. His father died soon after his birth, and his mother married Joseph Waller of New Milford (now Brookfield), Connecticut, in 1748.
In 1764, Peter Starr graduated from Yale. He taught school for three and a half years and studied theology with the Reverend Daniel Brinsmade (Yale 1745) of the Judea Society (Washington, Connecticut), and the Reverend Joseph Bellamy (Yale 1735) of Bethlehem, Connecticut.
Starr was licensed to preach by the Fairfield East Association of Ministers in 1769 and went to the East Greenwich Society in Kent (now the town of Warren), where Sylvanus Osborn was the minister. Osborn died in May, 1771, and Peter Starr was installed as pastor on May 18, 1772. He remained in this position for 57 years. In May, 1825, he was joined by the Reverend Hart Talcott, whose installation sermon is in the papers.
Peter Starr married Sarah Robbins, fourth daughter of the Reverend Philemon Robbins of Branford, on December 24, 1772. They had seven sons and two daughters. Sarah Robbins Starr died on July 7, 1809. Peter Starr then married Phebe Stevens, widow of the Reverend John Stevens (Yale 1779) of New Marlboro, Massachusetts. Phebe Stevens Starr died in 1832.
Peter Starr died at his home in Warren on July 17, 1829, at 85 years of age, the oldest Congregational clergyman in the state.
SYLVANUS OSBORN (ca. 1733-1771)
Sylvanus Osborn was pastor of the Church of the East Greenwich Society in Kent (now Warren), Connecticut, where Peter Starr began his ministerial duties in 1769. Reverend Osborn graduated from the College of New Jersey in 1754.
He married Abigail Noble, second daughter of Stephen and Sarah (Ferris) Noble of Kent. He died in 1771, and Peter Starr was installed as pastor in September of 1771.
Reverend Osborn's widow married Jeremiah Day, Sr., on October 7, 1772. She died in 1810.
JOHN KEEP (1749-1784)
John Keep was born on March 10, 1749, the younger son of Samuel and Sarah (Colton) Keep of Longmeadow, Massachusetts. His mother was the daughter of William and Hannah (Terry) Bement of Enfield, Massachusetts. John Keep's father died in 1761, and his mother married John Hale of Longmeadow in 1762.
John Keep studied theology with his pastor, Reverend Dr. Stephen Williams (Harvard College, 1713), graduated from Yale in 1769, and was licensed to preach by the Hampden Association of Ministers in January, 1771.
On March 4, 1772, John Keep was called to the Congregational Church in Sheffield (Berkshire County), Massachusetts, where he was ordained on June 10, 1772. He married Hannah Rebekah Robbins, the fifth daughter of Reverend Philemon Robbins of Branford, Connecticut, on March 2, 1775. He remained at Sheffield until his death on September 3, 1784. During the Revolutionary War, he was a chaplain to Captain Jonathan Smith's regiment, and there are a number of his camp sermons in this collection. John Keep was noted for his pulpit oratory.
John and Hannah Keep had no children. Reverend John Keep (Yale 1802) was a nephew. After John Keep's death, his widow married the Honorable Jahleel Woodbridge (Princeton College, 1761), of Stockbridge, Massachusetts, who died in August, 1796. Hannah Keep Woodbridge died on February 9, 1799, at the home of her sister Sarah, the wife of Reverend Peter Starr.
JOHN STEVENS (1750-1792)
John Stevens was born in Danbury, Connecticut, in 1750. He graduated from Yale in 1779 and was licensed to preach by the Litchfield South Association of Ministers in 1780. He was called to the Congregational Church of the New Concord Society in Chatham (Columbia County), New York, and was ordained on May 13, 1781.
Stevens married Phebe Warner, eldest child of Lemuel and Sarah (Gaylord) Warner of New Milford, Connecticut, in 1781. He was dismissed from Chatham in 1793 and began to organize a new mission in New Marlborough, South Parish, where he was officially installed on October 22, 1794. Here he remained until his death on January 6, 1799.
His widow Phebe married Peter Starr on October 24, 1810.
Bibliography: Biographical information obtained from Franklin Bowditch Dexter, Yale Biographies and Annals
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Connecticut; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Sermons; Clergy; Keep, John, 1749-1784; Osborn, Sylvanus, 1733-1771; Stevens, John, 1750-1799; Starr, Peter, 1744-1829
- PETER STARR SERMONS, 1769-1829; Series I; 6 linear feet (15 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The sermons are arranged chronologically. Undated sermons are organized by biblical text, if known, with funeral sermons, fragments, and notes at the end. One journal and one set of church meeting minutes have been placed at the end of the series.
  - 1769-1774 June (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
  - 1774 July - 1778 April (Box 2, Folder 13-24)
  - 1778 May-1781 (Box 3, Folder 25-35)
  - 1782 -1785 September (Box 4, Folder 36-46)
  - 1785 October - 1788 March (Box 5, Folder 47-53)
  - 1788 April - 1789 (Box 6, Folder 54-60)
  - 1790-1791 (Box 7, Folder 61-67)
  - 1792 - 1794 September (Box 8, Folder 68-79)
  - 1794 October -1798 April (Box 9, Folder 80-92)
  - 1798 May -1802 March (Box 10, Folder 93-104)
  - 1802 April -1806 March (Box 11, Folder 105-116)
  - 1806 April - 1808 Jul, 1808 September-1809 (Box 12, Folder 117-129)
  - 1810 -1815 (Box 13, Folder 130-142)
  - 1816-1829, undated (Box 14, Folder 143-150)
  - Sermons based on Old Testament texts, undated (Box 14, Folder 151)
  - Sermons based on New Testament texts, undated (Box 14, Folder 152-153)
  - Funeral sermons, undated (Box 14, Folder 154)
  - Fragments of sermons, undated (Box 14, Folder 155-156)
  - Fragments of sermons, undated (Box 15, Folder 157-160)
  - Notes for sermons, undated (Box 15, Folder 161)
  - Journal, 1770 June (Box 15, Folder 162)
  - Minutes of church meeting, 1774 August 31 (Box 15, Folder 163)
- SYLVANUS OSBORN SERMONS, 1758-1770; Series II; 0.25; (1 box)
  The sermons are arranged chronologically.
  - 1758 - 1770, undated (Box 16, Folder 1-7)
- JOHN KEEP SERMONS, 1770-1783; Series III; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  This Series is arranged chronologically.
  - 1770 - 1779 (Box 17, Folder 1-11)
  - 1780-1783, undated (Box 18, Folder 12-19)
- JOHN STEVENS SERMONS, 1780-1799; Series IV; 1 linear foot (2 boxes)
  This series is arranged chronologically, according to the numerical order of the sermons.
  - 1780 - 1788
    - #193 - #249 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - #250 - #298 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - #307 - #332 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - #333 - #359 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - #360 - #397 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - #403 - #432 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - #437 - #498 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - 1788 - 1789, #500 - #543 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - 1789, #547 - #598 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - 1790, #602 - #643 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - 1791, #644 - #669 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - 1791 Aug - Sep, #671 - #680 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - 1792 Jan - May, #685 - #699 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - 1792 Jun - Dec, #704 - #721 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - 1793, #722 - #751 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - 1793, #752 - #778 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - 1793, #779 - #785 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - n.d. (1780 - 1793), New Concord Society (Box 20, Folder 18-21)
  - n.d. (1793 - 1799), New Marlborough, South (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - undated (Box 20, Folder 23)
- MISCELLANEOUS SERMONS, undated; Series V; 0.25; (1 box)
  These sermons are all unidentified and undated.
  - Sermons, undated (Box 21, Folder 1-4)